Good morning, today's דף Daf is י"ג. Yud Gimmel. We pick up
at the bottom of י"ב עמוד ב', Yud Bais Amud Bais, two
lines from the bottom, ובאמת אמרו, V'emes Amru, where we're wrapping up
certain גזירות gezeirot they they had on שבת, Shabbat, activities they didn't
want you doing on שבת Shabbat because it could lead to a
transgression. So it started with carrying, which was the opening theme at
ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, and now we're into doing various things by
candlelight; you'll come to tip the candles. And then, as we'll see,
we will switch gears radically to another concern, not שבת-related, Shabbat but
doing one thing it'll lead to something else. So two lines from
the bottom, ובאמת אמרו החזן. V'emes Amru hachazzan. So even though you
can't read by candlelight, they said that the חזן, chazzan, who was
either the you know the person that obviously was helps you know
did a lot of the functions in the שול, shul, maybe also
was somebody that taught the kids, he can he can see where
to start the reading from for the kids. So apparently this is
interesting that the practice of מעביר סדרה ma'avir sedrah or learning the
ליינינג, laining, or learning of the פרשה parsha prior to שבת Shabbat
or on שבת, Shabbat, seems to have been a quite ancient practice.
So the גמרא Gemara says ואמרת רישא רואה, v'amarta reisha ro'eh, but
you said in the beginning that the חזן chazzan can you know
can see where the you know where you're reading from. So the
גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו לקרות? mai lav likros? So doesn't that
mean that you can actually read from it, which is obviously a
problem because if the if he can read, how does that fit
in with the principle that you are not allowed to read by
candlelight because you'll come to להטות? l'hattos? So the question is that
the משנה Mishna
says—where's the משנה? Mishna? I'm sorry, hold on, yes, thank you. The
משנה Mishna is ובאמת
אמרו החזן רואה היכן תינוקות קוראין אבל לא יקרא.
V'emes amru hachazzan
ro'eh heichan tinokos korin aval lo yikra. So it's just really trying,
that's a funny way of phrasing it, but it's really just trying
to figure out what is this reality of seeing without reading? Okay.
לא לסדר ראשי פרשיותיו, Lo l'sader rashei parshiyosav, to organize the beginning
of the פרשיות. parshiyos. Exactly what that means is not clear. The
רמב"ם Rambam says what it means is you know he can like
find the beginning, read the first two or three words to get
the kids started, and then the kids read the rest, but he
can't really do a you know a serious reading on his own.
He can just say oh where were we you know וידבר, Vayidaber,
oh here it is, and then read the first two or three
words. וכן אמר רבה בר שמואל אבל מסדר הוא ראשי פרשיותיו. V'chein
amar Rabbah bar Shmuel aval mesader hu rashei parshiyosav. He can sort
of like put in place the beginning of the פרשיות, parshiyos, get
them started, but he can't really read a lot. So the גמרא
Gemara says וכולה פרשה לא, V'chula parsha lo, he can't read the
whole פרשה? parsha? Top of י"ג עמוד א'. Yud Gimmel Amud Aleph.
מיתיבי, Meisivi, I'll ask you on this a תוספתא, Tosefta, רבן גמליאל
אומר התינוקות של בית רבן היו מסדרים פרשיותיהם וקורין לאור הנר. Rabban
Gamliel omer hatinokos shel beis rabban hayu mesadrim parshiyoseihen v'korin l'or haneir.
The young kids, literally infants, but it means like the small kids
of their master's house, because they would learn by a tutor, a
teacher of a group of kids, so that's the famous phrase תינוקות
של בית רבן, tinokos shel beis rabban, right, the young kids who
are learning in their master's house, they're learning like תורה Torah and
פרשה, parsha, היו מסדרים פרשיותיהם וקורין לאור הנר. hayu mesadrim parshiyoseihen v'korin
l'or haneir. So they would they would identify whatever, organize their פרשיות
parshiyos and they would read by candlelight. They, the תינוקות, tinokos, not
the adult. We're going to ask in a minute why do we
let them read? So the גמרא Gemara says so anyway, I'm sorry,
that's exactly the question. It says היו קוראין, hayu korin, they were
reading, not just that they would identify, but they would actually read,
היו קוראין לאור הנר. hayu korin l'or haneir. So the גמרא Gemara
says I know, so that's going to be the answer, but first
we're assuming that there shouldn't be a difference; like you know you
wouldn't like actively violate a דרבנן d'rabbanan with these kids presumably. So
the גמרא Gemara says right, alright, it's all really getting to פשט
pshat in the משנה. Mishna. איבעית אימא Ei bayis eima ראשי פרשיותיו,
rashei parshiyosav, when it says they read, it doesn't really mean they
read, it just means that they look read the beginning. ואיבעית אימא
V'ei bayis eima no, שאני תינוקות, shani tinokos, no, the kids can
do the full reading. Why? Now you could just say because they're
דרבנן d'rabbanan and they're you know under the age of חינוך chinuch
or whatever, but that's we don't want to go there. So we
say הואיל ואימת רבן עליהם לא אתי לאצלויי, Ho'il v'eimas rabban aleihem
lo asi l'atzloyei, because they're afraid of their רבי, Rebbe, so they're
you know they don't do anything without asking permission, so they won't
come to tip the candle. Even if it was a weekday, they
wouldn't, who would dare move the candle if if the רבי Rebbe
is there without asking the רבי's Rebbe permission?
Yeah, the kids' taste has changed.
Oh yeah. Well, or maybe it's of society and how we and
how much independence we give them. Anyway, so fine. That's wrapping up
the reading by candlelight. As I said, there's a more general idea
that could be at play, that even without אימת רבן, eimas rabban,
which is that when you have a group of people doing something,
then we're not as afraid because one person will remind the other.
And we had that yesterday, if multiple people are using the candle,
if they're doing their own reading, so they're not a group, they're
they're multiple individuals, not. But if they're doing it as a group,
then we're less afraid that one person will forget because the other
person will remind. Now we switch gears radically to a statement that's
has not related to שבת Shabbat at all. הזב לא יאכל עם
הזבה מפני הרגל עבירה, Hazav lo yochal im hazava mipnei hergel aveira,
a זב zav should not eat with a זבה, zava, it'll lead
to הרגל עבירה. hergel aveira. What this is doing in שבת, Shabbat,
as I mentioned the other day, it's possible that a whole list
of teaching of don't do A, it'll lead to B, were taught
together. Don't sit down for a haircut before מנחה, Mincha, you'll forget
about דאווענינג davening מנחה. Mincha. Don't do certain things before שבת Shabbat
on שבת; Shabbat; it'll lead to breaking שבת. Shabbat. זב Zav shouldn't
eat with a זבה; zava; it really has nothing to do with
שבת Shabbat per se, but that group of things was put here.
came מסכת שבת Masechet Shabbat because the core of it was dealt
with cases of שבת. Shabbat. That's one way of understanding. The other
way of understanding why we're dealing with a זב zav eating with
a זבה zava is because the גמרא Gemara the next משנה Mishna
is about to say, these are some of the things that were
taught in the עליה Aliyah of חנניה בן גוריון Chananya ben Guryon
and בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai agreed upon,
a whole list of גזרות Gezeirot that were part of a decision
of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, so it
could just be that this happened to be part of that list.
It wasn't specifically limited to שבת, Shabbat, but this was part of
that special list of eighteen things. We'll see about that a little
bit later today. Okay, but anyway, a זב zav should not eat
with a זבה, zava, it will lead to הרגל עבירה. hergel aveira.
Now, what does הרגל עבירה hergel aveira mean? So, as I explained
the other day, sort of following רש״י, Rashi, it means, here you
are, the טהור tahor people are all eating together. You have these
two people that are טמא, tamei, they can't eat with you. A
male זב zav and a female זבה. zava. So,
they can't eat with you, the טהור tahor people, so they have
to go off and eat by themselves, you know, go eat in
the טמא tamei room or whatever. But of course, they can't eat
because this is assuming, and we're actually going to see that in
the גמרא, Gemara, that everybody's being careful of הלכות טהרה hilchot tahara
even though they don't have to, even though they're not כהנים Kohanim
and it's not תרומה. terumah.
They can't eat their own food...
Yeah, so the assumption is, and we'll see that in the גמרא,
Gemara, they can't even eat their own food because it'll lead to
touching other people's food and so on. So that was the assumption,
you go off and do it on your own. But we don't
want a זב zav and a זבה zava eating by themselves in
private alone, it'll lead to them having sex, you know, they're in
private, nobody else is around, who knows what it will lead to?
Is this man with his wife?
Yeah. That's the way רש״י Rashi explains the issue, he says because
of a concern of ערווה erva and כרת. karet.
Now, you could even have gone so far to say, or not
so far, meaning, you could have said we're talking only about a
man and a woman who are not married to one another, and
maybe they דווקא davka seize the opportunity even if they're single or
whatever, you know, oh my god, they're alone, nobody is around, seize
the opportunity. But, you know, then presumably you would not have needed
a special גזירה, gezeira, then it would have fallen under general concerns
of ייחוד, yichud, other types of concerns. So רש״י Rashi again, this
is not explicit in the גמרא Gemara I should say, none of
this, רש״י Rashi again assumes we're talking, and רמב״ם Rambam as well,
husband and wife. Okay, so even though you're a husband and wife,
don't go off together and eat in private in the same room,
who knows where it will lead? Now, that's a little funny because
a husband and wife are allowed to eat together at home when
she's a נידה. niddah. So what all of a sudden is the
concern? So we'll talk about that in a minute, but by saying
husband and wife, it makes us... it'll lead to a discussion the
גמרא Gemara is going to have about general practices of נידה. niddah.
But I do want to say that there's another much easier interpretation
of this, it's not my own, I got this from... this I
told you there's this book out about the משנת ארץ ישראל Mishnat
Eretz Yisrael from the ספראי, Safrai, which is a brothers and then
his daughter also, חנה ספראי, Chana Safrai, anyway, but so a whole
little group...
חנה ספראי Chana Safrai was not his wife.
Oh really? She's single?
She died and she never married.
Oh I'm sorry, so my mistake.
Her father was שמואל ספראי. Shmuel Safrai. Her brother was זאב.
Ze'ev. I see, thank you, okay, my mistake, sorry. Okay, so it
was a father, daughter, and brother and son, all sort of put
out this edition about משניות Mishnayot and which the whole ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael context of these משניות. Mishnayot. So it was very nice,
it's quasi-popular, quasi-academic, but gives the whole historical sociological setting, brings in
all the academic discussions. Anyway, they have it on שבת Shabbat and,
you know, what they say is it's amazing how much I just
assumed רש״י, Rashi, they say a much more simple פשט pshat is
that, fine, we're talking about husband and wife, but the הרגל עבירה
hergel aveira is the immediate issue here about טומאה, tumah, meaning, as
רבקה Rivka was saying, of course we're going to assume a טמא
tamei person can't eat with a טהור tahor person, they might touch
your food and make it טמא. tamei. But not only that, we
don't even want a husband and wife who are both טמא tamei
eating together. Why? Because if it's two strangers טמא tamei eating together,
fine, just because you're טמא tamei you don't have to eat by
yourself, eat with your friend who's טמא. tamei. But if it's a
husband and wife who are both טמא tamei eating together, that'll easily
lead to the next time only one of them will be טמא,
tamei, but they're still husband and wife so they'll want to eat
together. And we don't want, right, a טמא tamei and a טהור
tahor person eating together because that'll lead to making the food טמא.
tamei. So specifically husband and wife is something we have to be
concerned about because they will be accustomed to eating together and then
they'll do it even when one is טהור. tahor. So according to
that approach, the concern has nothing to do with sex, it's just
a concern of טומאה, tumah, and specifically in the case of husband
and wife, even if they're both טמא, tamei, it'll lead to a
case where only one of them is טמא. tamei. Yes,
Michael.
Doesn't הרגל עבירה hergel aveira mean sex?
I
mean, and
it usually means sex. Yeah, it's a
good question, I'll have to
check.
תניא, Tanya, רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר
Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar אומר.
omer. So we start a ברייתא, braita, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar says: בוא וראה עד היכן פרצה טהרה בישראל. Bo
u'rei ad heichan partza tahara b'Yisrael. Come see how widespread purity
was in Israel even though we're not dealing with כהנים. Kohanim. and
we're not dealing with תרומה *Terumah*, but the practice of eating בטהרה
be'taharah *be'tahara* was so widespread שלא שנינו לא יאכל הטהור עם הטמא
*shelo shaninu lo yochal ha-tahor im ha-tamei*, like we don't just say
a טהור tahor, *tahor* person shouldn't eat with a טמא tamei, *tamei*
person, because that's taken for granted. Already nobody טהור tahor *tahor* eats
with anybody טמא tamei. *tamei*, even though there's really no prohibition nowadays
to if you know to eat your food בטומאה *be'tumah*, I mean,
unless you're a כהן *Kohen* and you're dealing with תרומה *Terumah*. So
really there would be you could eat טהור tahor *tahor* with a
טמא tamei. *tamei* person together. Nevertheless, the practice of eating בטהרה *be'tahara*
had been so widespread that not only did people take care to
eat בטהרה *be'tahara*, but they were even careful to eat not together
with טמא tamei, *tamei* people, so those טמא tamei. *tamei* people should
not impurify their food. By the way, as mentioned before, you know,
you see this in the Christian gospels, you know, the whole issue
about Jesus eating with the prostitutes and the tax collectors and all
of that, that the idea of these חבורות *chaburot* and you know,
חבר chaver *chaver*, which is you know, an eating group, and who's
on the inside, who's outside, who can eat with us, were things
which are really very sort of boundary-defining.
So anyway, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here, you know, so it's
sort of non-very democratic. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here sees that
as a very positive thing. You're so careful about טהרה *tahara* even
when it's not necessary, and it's already taken for granted that טמא
tamei, *tamei* people don't eat with טהור *tahor* people. That didn't need
to be said. אלא Ella *Ella*, so the only thing that needed
to be said was לא יאכל הזב עם הזבה מפני הרגל עבירה
aveira, *lo yochal ha-zav im ha-zava mipnei hergel aveirah*. All that needed
to be said was a זב zav *zav* and a זבה zavah
*zava* together shouldn't eat, even though they're both טמא tamei *tamei*, because
of הרגל עבירה aveira *hergel aveirah*. And again, what's the question of
הרגל עבירה *hergel aveirah*? Is it a sex question, is it a
טומאה tumah *tumah* question? Not clear. So let's take a look, and
you'll see also in the next line another ambiguity of where is
the concern of where things will lead. כיוצא בו *Keyotzei bo*, in
a similar way, לא יאכל זב פרוש zav parush עם זב עם
הארץ zav am ha'aretz. *lo yochal zav parush im zav am ha-aretz*.
Even two male זבים *zavim*, and here obviously talking about strangers or
you know not family, a זב zov *zav* who is generally careful
about eating בטהרה *be'tahara* should not eat with a זב zov *zav*
who is a you know commoner who's not usually so careful about
eating בטהרה *be'tahara*, maybe not usually so careful about taking תרומות ומעשרות
terumos u'maasros. *terumot u-ma'asrot*, right, this general category of עם הארץ am
ha'aretz *am ha-aretz*. Even they should not eat together. Why not? שמא
ירגילנו אצלו *Shema yargilennu etzlo*. So the same phrase of הרגל *hergel*,
accustom, maybe he'll be accustomed to be by him. What's so bad
he's accustomed to be by him? So let's take a look. וכי
מרגילו אצלו מאי הוי *Ve-chi margilo etzlo mai havei*? So what if
he's accustomed to be by him? It's the same we would wish
we would have had this discussion by the זב zov *zav* and
the זבה zavah *zava*, what's the concern? But they're having it here
by the זב zav. *zav* and the זב עם הארץ am ha'aretz
*zav am ha-aretz*. So what if they get accustomed to being together?
אלא אימא שמא יאכילנו דברים טמאים *Ella eima shema ya'achilennu dvarim tme'im*.
Maybe if they're eating together, the עם הארץ am ha'aretz. *am ha-aretz*
who's not so careful about טומאה וטהרה tumah ve'taharah *tumah ve-tahara* will
feed this one things that are טמא *tamei*. So the גמרא Gemara?
*Gemara* says, אטו זב פרוש לא דברים טמאים אכל *Atu zav parush
lo dvarim tme'im achal*? I don't get it. The other guy is
a זב *zav*, so he can eat דברים טמאים *dvarim tme'im*, what
are you concerned? So again, the thing is it seems like we're
concerned about something that's going to happen right now. So right now
they're both טמא *tamei*. What are you concerned about? אלא אימא *Ella
eima*, so the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says, אמר רבא Rava *Amar Rava*,
אביי *Abaye*, גזירה gezeirah שמא יאכילנו דברים שאינם מתוקנים *gezeirah shema ya'achilennu
dvarim she-einam metukanim*. We're afraid like Michael said, one of the things
an עם הארץ am ha'aretz, *am ha-aretz* is, an עם הארץ am
ha'aretz. *am ha-aretz* generally assumed to not be so careful about טומאה
וטהרה tumah ve'taharah... *tumah ve-tahara* and not be so careful about taking
תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'maasros *terumot u-ma'asrot* from their grain. So therefore once
you get once you're eating with him, he'll say here, have my
sandwich, and his sandwich will be made out of bread that's טבל
*tevel*. So you don't want to eat you know be together and
especially again if the idea is you can't eat with your normal
group because you're טמא *tamei*, then it might create a particular intimacy
for the טמאים *tme'im* that are eating together. We're all here in
this together, we're eating together, we're all טמאים *tme'im*, so that maybe
connection and intimacy which isn't normally around, maybe he'll ask you to
share his food, maybe it'll be stuff that is not taken תרומות
ומעשרות terumos u'maasros. *terumot u-ma'asrot*.
Yes. And that has nothing to do with being a זב *zav*,
that has to do
with dealing with an עם הארץ *am ha-aretz* versus a חבר *chaver*.
Right. So the assumption seems to be also generally that חברים chaverim,
*chaverim* generally wouldn't eat with עם הארץ *am ha-aretz*. Why? Because עם
הארץ *am ha-aretz* were generally assumed to be טמא *tamei*, they weren't
careful, חברים chaverim *chaverim* were not. So in general you wouldn't eat
we wouldn't have to tell you, you're eating with טהור *tahor* people,
you're not eating with the עם הארץ *am ha-aretz*. Like I said,
those those eating groups were very sort of much about boundaries and
exclusive and so on. But now today when you're טמא *tamei* and
you'll have to leave our group, what are you going to do?
Go off and eat by yourself? No, you'll go eat with the
עם הארץ *am ha-aretz*. So it's exactly the problem that you know
you are going and now joining this group that generally we sort
shun or general because you can't eat with us today, and then
we're concerned about the problems that that association will lead to. Okay.
So it doesn't have to specifically involve being a זב *zav*, this
could be you're טמא *tamei* for for any... Yeah, we're just talking
about right. Maybe a זב *zav*, that's a good point, maybe specifically
it picked the זב *zav* example because that was one that lasted
many days, right, so and therefore maybe it would be it wasn't
like it wasn't like something oh for today I'll go eat with
them and then I'll go to the מקוה mikvah, *mikvah* and I'll
be back with you tomorrow. So that's an interesting point why it
mentions זב *zav*. It could be because it would be an ongoing
problem, like least know for a week or so. So that's what
אביי *Abaye* says, we're afraid that you'll eat non-kosher food. רבא Rava
אמר *Rava amar*, and רבא *Rava* says, רוב עמי הארץ מעשרין rov
amei ha'aretz measrin. הן *Rov amei ha-aretz measrin hen*. We don't have
to be concerned about that. Normally we assume that even the עם
הארץ *am ha-aretz* take תרומות ומעשרות *terumot u-ma'asrot* because the general prohibition,
it's not prohibition, there's a general requirement when you buy grain from
an עם הארץ *am ha-aretz*, it's called דמאי demai. *demai*, we assume
that they took תרומה *Terumah*. because תרומה one little grain can exempt
the entire whatever, the entire warehouse, but we're not so certain they
took תרומות ומעשרות. So if you buy grain from an עם הארץ
you have to take תרומות ומעשרות again. But that's only דרבנן. derabbanan.
Biblically we assume that it's that the majority do it, it's only
a minority that don't, and therefore biblically we would it really would
be okay. So here רבא says, if we're making a safeguard, we
wouldn't make a safeguard maybe he'll give you his sandwich, because you
know what, if he gave you the whole problem about eating their
grain is only דרבנן derabbanan anyway. Biblically we can really assume that
their food is okay. So we're not going to make a safeguard
against this דרבנן derabbanan concern of דמאי. So that's not what the
problem would be. אלא here's the problem. שמא יהא רגיל אצלו ויאכילנו
דברים טמאים בימי טהרתו. Shema yehei ragil etzlo ve'yachilenu devarim teme'im bimei
taharato.
What Michael said. Not what's going to happen today, but what's going
to happen tomorrow. You're going to get so friendly and chummy with
this עם הארץ that even when you're טהור, you like his company
better than the, you know, your other group or you want to
go spend some time with him, you got to know him very
well over this last week when you were both טמא, and then
you'll eat with him when you're טהור and then you'll eat the
stuff that he has that is טמא. Okay, so that's the concern
about the זב part in the עם הארץ. Now what I should
say is again in terms of its relevance for the זב עם
הזבה zav im ha'zavah is that you see the גמרא Gemara. first
wanted to explain this that something wrong will happen right now. Right?
Right now something wrong is going to happen. You're going to have
his food. Oh his food is anyway טמא. But maybe it's not
תרומות ומעשרות. And then finally רבא said it's a fear of something
that will happen later in the future once you get this type
of intimacy. So that somewhat also could reflect the two ways of
reading this issue about what the זב והזבה zav ve'hazavah problem is.
The right now problem is not a problem about טמא, you're all
טמא. It's not a problem presumably about tomorrow you'll eat together when
we're talking about חברים, so that's not an issue of tomorrow you
eat together. So if the concern is right now, it's the way
רש״י Rashi understands, that the concern is it'll lead to them having
sex, they're in private and so on. If the concern is what
might happen tomorrow, then you could say we don't want them to
eat together today, exactly like we said for the זב פרוש and
the זב עם הארץ. Because then tomorrow they'll eat together when one
of them is טמא, maybe assuming husband and wife so they'll want
to be eating together, and therefore it'll be a טומאה tumah, problem.
So again it leaves open the question of what is the concern
of the זב והזבה. zav ve'hazavah. The reason I am emphasizing this
is because if the concern of the זב והזבה zav ve'hazavah is
husband and wife, and a concern that by being together and being
alone they'll come to have sex, then that raises questions about I
mean what do you mean? Husband and wife can eat their meals
in private even if she's a נדה. niddah. So keep that in
mind as we now go to the next סוגיא sugya because the
next סוגיא sugya now, although like you know we've seen some type
of very important discussions in שבת Shabbos that have nothing to do
in שבת Shabbos that you would have expected in their primary case.
So a day or two ago we had all these discussions about
תפילה tefillah and ערבית רשות arvit reshus and how does one stand
in תפילה tefillah and how does one sort of dress in תפילה.
tefillah. Now we're going to have a discussion about the הרחקות, harchakos,
the way husband and wife have to, can and cannot be together
during the period of נדה, niddah, which is not at all, which
is not discussed in מסכת נדה, Masechet Niddah, it's discussed here in
the middle of nowhere in מסכת שבת. Masechet Shabbos. Okay, so we're
about to see that.
See and if it's, if it's a husband and wife kind of
thing and you're worried about טומאה tumah וטהרה then it could be
if they're both טמא or טהור for any reason, not just זב
וזבה, zav ve'zavah, right?
If you're afraid about them, about them having sex?
No, טומאה וטהרה... yeah, if they're both... I mean... Oh you mean
again why specifically the זב והזבה zav ve'hazavah example? I would assume
the זב והזבה zav ve'hazavah example is because by the woman that
is something that's more common, although זבה zavah is uncommon and you
really wonder why it didn't say נדה, niddah, right? So that I,
that I understand, I don't understand why in her case it's jumping
to זבה zavah as opposed to נדה niddah unless again זבה zova.
is something that could be נדה niddah in the תורה Torah is
only exactly one week from the beginning of the bleeding to a
week after, no matter how many clean days or non-clean days. זבה
zova, could be a very long time because without seven clean days
in a row it could keep on stretching on and on. So
the only reason I could imagine that it's emphasizing זב וזבה zav
ve'zavah is because that could be a long period together and that's
particularly a concern of the intimacy that grows up during that time.
Yes, רבקה. Rivka.
Doesn't this set up a different classist- Yes.
Yes, that is, that's what I was alluding to before. Right, that's
what I was alluding to before that the whole חברים and the
אוכלים בטהרה ochlim be'taharah and the עמי הארץ. amei ha'aretz. Being concerned
about עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz because number one טומאה, but that's like
a self-created problem because we've decided to eat בטהרה so now the
טומאה is an issue, and number two the מעשרות maasros issue, which
is also like דרבנן derabbanan as we've seen רוב עמי הארץ מעשרין.
But those things, yes, serve to create a definite class division and
a lot of, there's a lot of issues about the degree of
interaction a non-עם הארץ, a חבר can have with an עם הארץ.
You're absolutely correct. Look, that's the whole point as I was saying
about you know like when it speaks about eating with the tax
collectors and the prostitutes or whatever is to sort of say we
shouldn't have these hierarchies and divisions, it should all be very equal
and democratic.
But yes, where it actually matters.
Well, that's true also, although it wasn't limited to just
כהנים, kohanim, but whatever. But the attitude carries on as one person
eats חלב
ישראל cholov Yisroel
and the other doesn't.
Right. You're absolutely correct. Right. You're absolutely correct. The one question I
have that I have not sort of looked at rigorously is, is
that a lot of times with this whole discussion of a חבר
ועם הארץ, Chaver ve’Am Ha’aretz, it's the גמרא Gemara discussing the משנה.
Mishnah. The question is how much did that reality continue in the
time of the גמרא? Gemara I think there's not, I have to
check, but I think that that's, clearly this issue of חולין בטהרה
Chullin b’Tahara and these divisions, as you say, these class divisions, I
think, I think I don't know how long that lived the משנה,
Mishnah, how long that was true in the time of the גמרא.
Gemara We saw today in other forms. Right. Right, but it is
worth, right, I agree with that, but it is worth noting that
a lot of this discussion is in reference to, you know, the
Mishnaic realities. But you're right, it does, those issues about, you know,
religious practices as creating class divisions definitely is a reality.
It's
simply in certain Orthodox circles, and the ישיבה Yeshiva
graduates are mixed with people who never had that background, there's such
an arrogance and a sense of hubris.
Right. It's a problem.
And you know what? And I'm concerned that that's what divides us
to a point where young people move away. We wonder why we
lose young people, that we don't address this in the community. I
know we're getting off topic.
Yeah. But it's, look, I agree it's a big problem. I don't
know if I would say that's the whole problem about why people
go away, but you're right. But that issue, look, that's a, that's
in a way an innate problem in religion, you know, where, I
mean on religion, but anyway, but certainly where there's a question about
observance and where particularly I would say where religion is concerned about
sort of drawing the lines of who's, who's in and who's out
and so on. It could be other sociological realities as well, which
is about how much are you part of a core group and
doing these practices and creating sense of in and out and center
and margin and yes, it's definitely a problem. Yeah, it's certainly not,
not unique to Judaism, it's not unique to religion as well. There
are other ways in which, you know, groups are formed. All right.
So let's, yes, these are definitely, these are definitely issues. Let's now
continue in the גמרא. Gemara So it says like this: איבעיא להו,
Iba’ya lehu, they raised the following question. נדה, Niddah, מהו שתשן עם
בעלה, mahu shetishun im ba’alah, היא בבגדה והוא בבגדו? hi bevigda ve’hu
bevigdo?
So this seems like it's coming out of the blue, but we
will see that it's not.
And the question is can husband and wife sleep together in the
same bed when the woman is a נדה? Niddah? Now, what does
it mean היא בבגדה והוא בבגדו? hi bevigda ve’hu bevigdo? It doesn't
mean that they're wearing their business suits to bed. It means that
they're wearing pajamas because as רש"י Rashi points out, the גמרא Gemara
is clear that husband and wife are supposed to sleep together naked
actually. שארה כסותה ועונתה לא יגרע She’erah kesutah ve’onatah lo yigra
means that there's קירוב בשר. kiruv basar. There's actually a גמרא Gemara
in כתובות Ketubot that if, that if a man says, you know,
against the whole myth of like the hole in the sheet or
whatever, there's a גמרא Gemara that says that if the man says
I, I refuse to sleep with my wife unless she's wearing pajamas,
you know, unless we're, you know, they're, when, then she can force
a גט. get. Because they're actually part of the requirements of עונה
Onah is not just sex, but actually the physical closeness and sleeping
together naked. And that was taken for granted that that's husband, how
husband and wife would sleep. So the question is fine, let's say
you do something different when she's a נדה. Niddah. Let's say they
both wear pajamas. So there's a clear היכר, heker, it's a different
way, you know, it's obvious that something is different. So maybe they
should be allowed to sleep together and there's not a concern that
it will lead to sex. Okay? And or not? Or do they
need separate beds, which we know what the conclusion is. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. So אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav
Yosef, תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. העוף עולה עם הגבינה
על השולחן ואינו נאכל. Ha’of oleh im hagevinah al hashulchan ve’eino ne’echal.
So talk about striking examples from out of the blue. It says
you can eat poultry to, and you can have poultry and cheese
on the table at the same time, but you can't eat them
together. דברי בית שמאי. Divrei Beit Shammai. But we're not concerned that
you'll come to have some cheese with your chicken just because they're
on the table at the same time. בית הלל אומרים, Beit Hillel
omrim, בית הלל Beit Hillel says לא עולה ולא נאכל. lo oleh
velo ne’echal. No,
not only can you not eat them together, you can't have them
at the table at the same time. So you see, we're concerned,
this is obviously, we're not making a specific נדה Niddah question. It's
a general question about which actually fits very nicely in the theme
of these last משניות. Mishnayot. When are we concerned that A will
lead to B? Right? Or what type, can you do something that
will, that will say there's enough of a safeguard here that we're
not concerned A will lead to B? So it says look, בית
הלל Beit Hillel is concerned that you'll take some cheese with your
chicken because it's right there in front of you. So we should
have a similar concern that a husband and wife will have sex
if they're sleeping together. They're right, the opportunity is right there in
front of them. All right, all right. Anyway, fine. So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. So, so is that a good comparison?
So the גמרא Gemara says no. שאני התם, Shani hatam, there it's
different. I just want the phrase, דליכא דעות. d’leika de’ot. As Michael
said, the cheese and the, the cheese and the chicken don't have
their own opinion about it. So, so what's that old joke about
the difference between committed and, do you know those stories, I mean,
whatever, something about, something about the difference between involved and committed? Like
it's, I don't know, it's like a turkey on Thanksgiving, it's I,
whatever. This one is involved. The turkey is committed. So anyway, but
I forget it, it's a good line. Anyway, so he says look,
the cheese and the chicken don't have their opinion about it, so
you'll eat them, they're inanimate objects, they're in front of you. But
here, if we... one of them, the husband or wife, starts to
initiate sex, the other one hopefully will remember. So there's two opinions
there, there's two people there, so hopefully one of them will remember,
so that might make it okay.
He said just like the זב והזבה. Zav and the Zavah.
Alright, well we're getting there. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
הכי נמי מסתברא, Hachi nami mistabra, that makes sense that that makes
a difference. דהיכא דאיכא דעות שאני, Deheicha deika deot shani, if there's
two people involved it's different. דתני סיפא, Detani seifa, we taught at
the end of that משנה Mishnah about cheese and chicken. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל אומר, שני אכסנאין אוכלין על שולחן אחד, Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel omer shenei achsanain ochlin al shulchan echad, two guests in an
inn that are strangers can share a table, זה בבשר וזה בגבינה
ואין חוששין, zeh bavasar vezeh bigvinah ve'ein chosheshin,
one eats meat and one eats cheese and they don't have to
worry. You can eat and sit down next to another person because
if you want to reach over and grab their cheese, or you
ask them, you're not stealing it, 'Hey, could I have a little
piece of the cheese?' hopefully he'll remember. No, but hopefully he'll remember.
So if there's two people involved, then we are not concerned that
it'll lead to a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute,
ולאו איתמר עלה? velav itmar alah? One minute, but we qualify that.
אמר רב חנין בר אמי אמר רב שמואל, Amar Rav Chanin bar
Ami amar Rav Shmuel, לא שנו אלא שאין מכירין זה את זה.
Lo shanu ela she'ein makirin zeh et zeh. That's only if they're
strangers, they don't recognize one another. אבל מכירין זה את זה אסורין.
Aval makirin zeh et zeh asurin. But if they recognize one another,
it's forbidden. So if you're a stranger, you wouldn't even have the
gall to ask, 'Can I have a piece of your cheese?' So
that's why it's not a problem. But if you're friends, you say,
'Oh, could I have a bit?' and once you're comfortable and asking,
we're afraid you'll come to have some of their cheese with your
chicken. So you see it is a problem and we're not and
we don't say he'll remind you. So even though there are two
people, if you feel comfortable with one another, we're assuming it could
lead to something and we're not going to say the other guy
will remind you. And that should be like our case of husband
and wife. והא הכא נמי מכירין זה את זה נינהו, veha hacha
nami makirin zeh et zeh ninhu, here too they recognize one another,
we know that's the case. So therefore it should be a problem
because even though there are two people, it could lead to something.
So the גמרא Gemara says no. הכי השתא? Hachi hashta? What type
of a comparison is that? התם דעות איכא שינוי ליכא. Hatam deot
ika shinui leika.
In the cheese and meat case, yes there are two people and
we're concerned it'll lead to something, but that's because you didn't do
anything to make it unusual. You didn't do anything as a סימן,
siman, as a sign, as a mark to remind you that be
careful, there's a problem here. But here, הכא איכא דעות ואיכא שינוי.
Hacha ika deot veika shinui. There are two things: A, there are
two people involved, so hopefully one of them will remember, and B,
there's something there that's a היכר, heker, that's different, that's there to
mark and to remind you: you're wearing your pajamas, you're not naked
yet. And therefore hopefully the combination of that two will mean that
at least one of you guys will remember and it won't lead
to anything. So if you go by normal principles of when are
we concerned A will lead to B, you should not be concerned
with husband and wife sleeping together in the same bed wearing pajamas.
There are two factors to say that will not lead to something,
to having sex. Number one, they're two people, one of them should
remember, and number two, there's a היכר, heker, something is different in
order to remind them. Yes.
What's the law about touching?
So it's a good question. What David is saying is, but even
if they're not having sex, maybe they'll be physically touching and intimate
even without sex. So let's get back to that for now, let
us assume that we are,
you know what, let's hold on that, okay? Because it'll be relevant
in the next line. But that's a very good question. Aren't there
other concerns even without getting to sex?
Okay, so we're
going to get to the זב והזבה. Zav and the Zavah. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. תא שמע. Ta shema.
Now by the way, איכא דאמרי, ika de'amri, others say: תא שמע.
Ta shema. Same basic conclusion but just starting from a different place.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, we don't
start from בית הלל ובית שמאי, Beit Hillel veBeit Shammai, we go
straight to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל אומר Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, שני אכסנאין אוכלין על
שולחן אחד, Shenei achsanain ochlin al shulchan echad, זה בשר וזה גבינה.
zeh basar vezeh gvinah. ואיתמר עלה, Ve'itmar alah, and then we also
don't stop at that point but we just go straight to the
qualifier: ואיתמר עלה אמר רב חנין בר אמי אמר שמואל לא שנו
אלא שאין מכירין זה את זה אבל מכירין זה את זה אסור,
Ve'itmar alah amar Rav Chanin bar Ami amar Shmuel lo shanu ela
she'ein makirin zeh et zeh aval makirin zeh et zeh asur, that
you can't have cheese and meat together at the table if the
two people recognize one another. So that seems to be exactly analogous.
והני נמי מכירין זה את זה נינהו, Vehani nami makirin zeh et
zeh ninhu, and just like our case of husband and wife in
the bed they know one another, so it should be a problem.
And the answer is no, התם דעות איכא שינוי ליכא, hatam deot
ika shinui leika, in the cheese and the meat case, yes there
are two people but there's nothing unusual about it; הכא איכא דעות
ואיכא שינוי, hacha ika deot veika shinui, here there are both two
people and something unusual. Now, by the way, about the cheese and
the meat case, that's why if you are eating together with somebody
and you put up a סימן, siman, it's okay. So if I'm,
we're sitting together for lunch and I'm taking out my pastrami sandwich
and you're taking out your whatever yogurt, cheese sandwich, so I can
put a divider between us, I can have, make sure let's one
of us will eat on a mat and the other not on
a mat, some type of a סימן, siman, and then it works.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara is setting up. If you have
two people and a סימן, siman, then you're okay, you assume somebody
will remember. But if that's true, by the bed it should be
okay. So let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes. And now we
see why it's going to be brought in in our discussion. Not
only is it talking about general A leading to B, but it
specifically brings in our משנה Mishnah about the זב והזבה. Zav and
the Zavah. תא שמע, Ta shema, come in here. לא יאכל הזב
עם הזבה משום הרגל עבירה. Lo yokhal haZav im haZavah mishum hergel
averah. Don't eat together, it'll lead to something. Again, what's the, we
discussed what it might lead to. But by analogy I would say
to the cases of the meat and the cheese, and by analogy
I would say to the cases about the husband and wife and
the bed, it again seems like רש"י's Rashi reading that it will
lead to something right now, meaning by being together, something is going
to happen right now that we're concerned about, right? Just like the
concern you'll eat the cheese and the meat together, the husband and
wife will have sex, it's not what might happen in the future.
Right now something will happen. So presumably it's a concern they're eating
together it will lead to sex. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so why you see we do have that problem? So it says,
no, הכא נמי דאיכא שינוי ליכא, hacha nami de'ika shinui leika, same
point. Yes there's two people involved, but there's nothing there to be
a היכר heker to remind them. Okay, now, it's a little funny
again cause the idea of היכר heker is something that you need
if you forget, if you're not thinking. Oh my gosh, I wasn't
thinking, I just saw the cheese and I just popped it in
my mouth, I wasn't thinking about the fact that I was פליישּיג.
fleishig. Or the husband and wife are together in the bed, and
they're not remembering the כיס kis and נידה. niddah.
Here we're talking if it's the way רש"י Rashi understands, that it's
not just you forget, oh, I forgot we weren't married to one
another.
Or, I guess that's if they're single, that's if they're single but
that's not what רש"י Rashi says anyway. רש"י Rashi says that they're
married but she's a זבה. zova So I guess you could say
I
forgot that the reason we're together is because she's a זבה, zova
I'm a זב and whatever, so we just went ahead and it
led to sex, and we did forget what the reality was. Same
way you forgot you're פליישּיג fleishig or you forgot that when they're
together in the bed at the same time together they're in נידה.
niddah. So it seems like there a היכר heker would work. Everywhere
the problem that you knew exactly what was up but your יצר
הרע yetzer hara was getting the better of you, right, it's not
so clear why we would think a היכר heker would do any
good. Okay, a היכר heker just reminds, so, but it seems therefore
that the concern is not that your יצר הרע yetzer hara gets
the better of you, the concern is that you forget the specifics
of the circumstances, and therefore we say let a היכר heker work.
But in the case of the זב and the זבה zavah. there
was no היכר, heker, in our case there is a היכר heker
and therefore
it should be okay, right?
And which could mean that if you would have a היכר heker
in the זב and the זבה zavah, it could be okay, exactly.
So let's keep on going, תא
שמע, ta shema, okay, so we still don't have an answer, maybe
the היכר heker should make it okay. Come and hear, אל ההרים
לא אכל ועיניו לא נשא אל גלולי בית ישראל, el heharim lo
achal ve'einav lo nasa el gillulei beit yisrael, so he did not
look up, this is talking
about
a צדיק, tzadik, he did not eat towards the mountains, which might
mean in the context like עבודה זרה, avodah zarah,
but the way the גמרא Gemara explains it is it means he
didn't eat by merit of the mountains, by merit of the אבות,
avot, meaning he doesn't rely on זכות אבות, zechut avot, he has
his own זכות, zechut, ועיניו לא נשא אל גלולי בית ישראל, ve'einav
lo nasa el gillulei beit yisrael, he did not give sort of
worship the abominations of Israel, he wasn't עובד עבודה זרה, oved avodah
zarah, ואת אשת רעהו לא טימא, ve'et eshet re'ehu lo timme, he
did not defile his friend's wife, he did not commit adultery, ואל
אשה נידה לא יקרב, ve'el isha niddah lo yikrav,
and he did not draw close to a woman who was a
נידה. niddah. That drawing close often means having sex, right? It's echoing
the פסוק, pasuk, ואל אשה בנידת טומאתה לא תקרב לגלות ערותה, ve'el
isha beniddat tumatah lo tikrav legalot ervatah, do not draw near to
uncover her nakedness. So, געזונטהייט, gesundheit, in פשט pshat it might just
mean that he didn't have sex, but here's what the גמרא Gemara
says with it.
מה אשה נידה לאשת רעהו, mah isha niddah le'eshet re'ehu, it connects
a נידה, niddah, his wife who's a נידה niddah to his friend's
wife. מה אשת רעהו הוא בבגדו והיא בבגדה אסור, mah eshet re'ehu
hu bevigdo vehi bevigdah assur, the same way a friend's wife, you
should not be in bed with your friend's wife even if you're
both wearing pajamas, so אף אשתו נידה הוא בבגדו והיא בבגדה אסור,
af ishto niddah hu bevigdo vehi bevigdah assur, the same with a
man's wife when she's a נידה, niddah, they should not be in
bed together wearing pajamas. Now, why? Meaning, okay, you quoted a פסוק,
pasuk, you made a היקש, hekesh, still explain to me why? You've
already told me you're not concerned that it will lead to something
else because two people, there's a היכר, heker, so what does this
פסוק, pasuk, what's the reason at the end? So there are three
answers here, רש"י, Rashi, תוספות, Tosafot, and the רמב"ם. Rambam. רש"י Rashi
says, and it starts with a question why you can't be with
אשת רעהו eshet re'ehu הוא בבגדו והיא בבגדה. hu bevigdo vehi bevigdah.
So רש"י Rashi says there's an איסור ייחוד issur yichud and
therefore by analogy a man can't be with his wife who's a
נידה. niddah. תוספות Tosafot says what are you trying to suggest? You're
trying to suggest there's an איסור ייחוד issur yichud of husband and
wife together as a נידה? niddah? We know that's not true. Of
course not, husband and wife can be together in the same bedroom.
So he rejects רש"י Rashi because now רש"י Rashi might not have
said that, but he says that's why you can't be with another
person's wife and then just by
analogy a man can't be with his wife who's a נידה niddah
even without explaining why. תוספות Tosafot says who's trying to find a
common reason between the two, right, says that the concern here is
that even though there's היכר heker and there's דעות, de'ot, right, the
יצר הרע yetzer hara of sex, especially when it's such a sort
of immediate present opportunity, such a tempting opportunity,
will override your understanding of what you should and should not do.
So the same way that would clearly be אסור assur a man
with another man's wife together in bed even with their pajamas, because
obviously we'd consider a concern that the sex drive would override their
normal sort of their normal barriers. So even that's true about a
husband and wife being together in the same bed even if they're
wearing pajamas, it's a concern that the יצר הרע yeitzer hara will
get the better of him. That's what תוספות Tosfos says. The רמב"ן
Ramban has I think the best explanation, which goes to what David
says. David says, the רמב"ן Ramban says, he says, well, wait, you
mean to tell me the only reason a man can't be with
another man's wife together in bed in pajamas is because it might
lead to sex? He says, of course it's not why it's אסור.
assur. It's אסור assur even intrinsically. They're having a physical intimacy
together and certainly they could be having a sexual touch intentionally and
even not
intentionally, just being
physically touching, even if they're touching through their pajamas and all that
type
of—that's intrinsically problematic for somebody to do, a man to be doing
with another man's wife. It's on its own terms, that's improper behavior.
And the רמב"ן Ramban says, and therefore that's what the גמרא Gemara
is saying here as well, that even if you're together in bed,
even if they have pajamas and even if it's going to be
fine and we believe you're not going to have sex, it's still
a problem. You shouldn't be right up next to each other together
in bed together and having that type of physical and intentionally sexual
or certainly has sexual, it's erotic, it could have those types of
vibes even if that wasn't what was intended together when there's an
איסור issur of sex and when husband and wife are supposed to
be off limits to one another. So the רמב"ן Ramban reads it
not as a concern of יצר הרע yeitzer hara getting the better
of you, but a concern that this is intrinsically problematic. And that
gets to the issue about husband and wife, it's not only sex,
but it's sexual touch, it's other types of sort of sexual activity,
even if it does not lead to—you have a הכר heker with
pajamas. No, I'm saying—even if you
have another הכר.
heker. Yeah,
but even תוספות Tosfos would say that for יצר הרע. yeitzer hara.
Now I should say that this debate is an ongoing question about
what is the nature of the, what we call הרחקות, harchakos, the
way husband and wife have to be separate during נדה niddah beyond
just the איסור issur of sex. There are basically two approaches in
the ראשונים. Rishonim. One approach is the reason that certain types of
things they don't do together is because we're afraid if they do
A, it'll lead to B, it'll lead to C, and then they'll
have sex. So it's all about a גזירה that it'll lead to
sex, and we're concerned about this strong יצר הרע yeitzer hara of
sex will override our normal sense of keeping הלכה. halacha. And the
other concern is what the רמב"ן Ramban says, even if it doesn't
lead anywhere, the sort of physical intimacy is itself a problem at
the time when, if you're not supposed to be having sex, then
you shouldn't be having sexual intimacy, even if it is not sex
itself. It's sort of like the phrase the רמב"ן Ramban uses is,
it's like a חצי שיעור, chatzi shiur, like a qualitative חצי שיעור.
chatzi shiur. The same
way you shouldn't eat a כזית kazayis of something forbidden, so you
shouldn't have a half of a כזית. kazayis. So also the same
way you shouldn't be having sex, you shouldn't be having sexual activity.
It's
in the ambit of the prohibition, even if it won't actually lead
to the core prohibition itself. Yes.
They needed a פסוק pasuk in נביא Navi for a הכר? heker?
Okay, a good point. But anyway, but it strengthens the argument.
Let's keep on going. So how do we deal with a זב
וזבה zav v'zavah then? Husband and wife as a זב. So they're
not—I'll get to it.
Okay, let's read some more. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay,
שמע מינה, shma mina, ופליגא דרב פדת, u'pliga d'Rav Padda, this argues
on רב פדת. Rav Padda. דאמר רב פדת, d'amar Rav Padda, לא
אסרה תורה אלא קורבה של גילוי עריות בלבד. lo asra Torah ela
kurva shel gilluy arayos bilvad. The Torah only forbade actual sex itself,
not other things that were not sex, but intimate sexual contact and
so on, not that.
Subjective intimacy, is that what you're saying?
Yes, well, yes. But let's take a look at how this is—שנאמר
איש איש אל כל שאר בשרו לא תקרבו לגלות ערוה. shene'emar ish
ish el kol she'er besaro lo tikrevu legalos ervah.
So it's only לא תקרבו לגלות ערוה, lo tikrevu legalos ervah, it's
only about sex, it's not about other types of prohibitions. Now the
question that the ראשונים Rishonim ask is, okay, but we weren't saying
it was דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. Fine, he says דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, biblically it's only
sex itself. But who was saying biblically? We were saying דרבנן. d'Rabanan.
So רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosfos have ways that they try to
explain that somehow because he's emphasizing limiting it, somehow that means that
he would not go so far in the rabbinic prohibitions as well
and they have different explanations. But again I will tell you what
the רמב"ן's Ramban read of this, which is I think by far
the best. The רמב"ן Ramban says when the גמרא Gemara, sometimes says
לא אסרה תורה, lo asra Torah, it doesn't just mean that it's
not biblically אסור. assur. לא אסרה תורה lo asra Torah is a
way of saying it's not אסור, assur, even דרבנן. d'Rabanan. Now, what
does he mean? The only thing that's אסור assur is sex, so
other types of sexual activity are allowed? So the רמב"ן Ramban actually
says yes, with one qualifier. He quotes the פסוק pasuk אל כל
שאר בשרו. el kol she'er besaro. What is שאר? she'er? So the
רמב"ן Ramban says שאר she'er means a relative. So there are two
types of forbidden sex in the Torah. There's sex with like a
married woman, a man having sex with a married woman, and then
there's sex with your relatives and then your wife when she's a
נדה. niddah. So the רמב"ן Ramban says relatives and wife is שאר,
she'er, your flesh. And as opposed to another man's wife. And what
the רמב"ן Ramban says what רב פדת Rav Padda is saying, of
course a man can't be with another man's wife together in bed
with pajamas. Like, it's intrinsically problematic, sexual activity, the whole thing, I
get that. But when it comes to your sister, your daughter... mother,
your wife, there we're not concerned that of things that are not
sexual activity per se. So the same way we're going to see
in a minute you can give your sister a hug and a
kiss on the cheek and so on, you can do it for
a man's wife as well, although there's a different logic presumably for
the sister it's because we're assuming he doesn't have sexual feelings, bracketing
all these issues of incest, and whereas for a man's wife it
might be a different issue because they'll be having sex together in
a week or two so it's not as big of a the
temptation is great. But the argument the way the רמב"ן Ramban says
it's not he's just saying biblically it's not a problem. What he's
saying is actually if it's not by another man's wife that's a
problem and even things that aren't sex. But with your relatives with
a man's relative or with a man's wife only sex itself is
a problem not these other things.
Can I get back to the pajamas?
Yes, yes, just wait. Okay so that's what he says. Okay. עולא
Ulla so now we'll have a similar statement about that about relating
to relatives. כי הוי אתי מבי רב ki havi asi mibei rav
when he would come from the house of רב Rav after let's
say learning in ישיבה yeshiva and he'd come home after a while
הוה מנשק לה לאחוותיה havi minashek lela-achvosei
he would give his sister a kiss אבי חדייהו abei chadaiyu on
their chest. ואמרי לה ve-amri lei אבי ידייהו abei yadayu and some
say
on the back of their hand.
So I don't know if
that makes any sense to you.
And some say אבי ידייהו abei yadayu on... I don't... Bobby I
don't know what to do with this.
Have you seen anybody do that?
No no I don't know what to do with it. Moving on.
Okay so anyway I don't know what to say. Anyway but the
point is to not feel that as long as it now he
would not do that presumably with a married man's wife the way
the רמב"ן Ramban reads it. If you don't read it the way
the רמב"ן Ramban is it could be with even with a married
man's wife if it's non-sexual. But the way the רמב"ן Ramban reads
it it's specifically with his sister it was not a problem. ופליגי
דידיה אדידיה upligi didei adidei and this he argues on himself דאמר
עולא de'amar Ulla because he said in another place אפילו שום קורבה
אסור afilu shum korva assur any
any type of connection of touch and intimacy is forbidden משום לך
לך אמרי נזירא סחור סחור לכרמא לא תקרב mishum lech lech amri
nezira sechor sechor lecharma lo sikrav they say go around go around
go they say to the נזיר nazir
don't even get close to the vineyard. Stay away from things that
could be temptations. So obviously the question is what it mean he
argues on himself so how is he being consistent? So תוספות Tosafos
says the point is that there's a general guideline for people that
we don't want them to have certain types of touch because we're
concerned about it leads to sexual thoughts and sexual activities. But if
you know that for you it's a non-issue you can give your
sister a kiss and it's a completely neutral thing or whatever or
your 80-year-old aunt a kiss or whatever so then it's not a
problem. So that does lead this גמרא Gemara is very rich and
leads to these types of questions. How formally forbidden is touch that
is not sexual touch
to married women, relatives, the whole types of things? Is that forbidden
דרבנן? derabbanan? If it not forbidden it's just a safeguard and a
guideline and if you for you it's not an issue it's not
a problem. How about if it's sexual touch and so on? Presumably
even when רב פדת Rav Pedas said that the תורה Torah only
אסר assar sex itself presumably he would not want a person a
man to be having sexual touch with with his sister. Okay even
if it's not sex. Or sexual touch with his wife when she's
a נדה. niddah. So presumably even with the רמב"ן's Ramban or daughter,
even with the רמב"ן's Ramban explanation presumably here we're talking about touch
which is not intended to be sexual but could have could lead
to could have sexual resonance. Okay and therefore the argument would be
maybe it would not be a problem with a wife, a sister
and so on if you know for you it's not an issue
and that might allow sleeping together in the same bed. That's all
with רב פדת Rav Pedas but as a general rule I mean
so again there's interesting questions about how strictly אסור assur is it
touch which is non-sexual. Like for
example I'll just end with this point here for this because it's
too big of a discussion but look what's about shaking hands right?
Can you shake hands and so on? So some people say well
it's אסור דרבנן assur derabbanan but כבוד הבריות kavod habriyos it overrides
and so on. Some would argue it might not even be אסור
דרבנן assur derabbanan if it's a really neutral touch which is not
going to have any sexual resonance for you then there's no איסור
issur at all. That might be like the עולא Ulla case. Okay.
So there is this question about non-sexual touch how אסור assur is
it the רמב"ן's Ramban whole idea of maybe making a distinction between
relatives versus non-relatives and that gets into all of these issues. But
I would say for us the point is that the גמרא Gemara
certainly seems to conclude with רב פדת's Rav Pedas side that husband
and wife together in bed with pajamas is אסור assur A according
to תוספות Tosafos because the יצר הרע yetzer hara will get the
better of you and B according to the רמב"ן Ramban because that
is intrinsically problematic it is or will lead to sexual touch if
not sex itself but at least it'll lead to sexual touch and
that is a problem.
What about the husband of an אשת איש eshes ish though? If
there's no sexual touch there are no other types...
I got it we still have more גמרא Gemara, to go I
will be getting back to it I've not forgotten you Michael. Okay
now four lines from the bottom. תנא דבי אליהו Tana D'Bei Eliyahu
we taught in the school of אליהו Eliyahu this from אבות דרבי
נתן Avos D'Rabbi Nasan מעשה בתלמיד אחד ma'aseh betalmid echad there's a
story of once a student ששנה הרבה sheshanah harbeh he learned a
lot of משנה Mishnah וקרא הרבה vekarah harbeh he learned a lot
of פסוקים Psukim he learned a lot of תורה. Torah.
he attended many Torah sages. Again, it's not clear that he learned
a lot of גמרא, Gemara, but at least he was around the
rabbis a lot. ומת בחצי ימיו, Umes bachatzi yamav,
he died in half of his days. He died a very young
man. והייתה אשה נוטלת תפיליו ומחזירתן בבתי כנסיות ובבתי מדרשות, Vehaysa isha
noteles tefilav umechaziratan bevatei kneysiyos ubevatei midrashos, his wife took his tefillin
and started going to the various synagogues and study halls. ואמרה להן,
Veamra lahen, and she would say to the sages there, כתיב בתורה,
Kesiv baTorah, it's written in the Torah, כי הוא חייך ואורך ימיך,
Ki hu chayecha veorech yamecha, the Torah is your life, the length
of your days. בעלי ששנה הרבה וקרא הרבה ושימש חכמים הרבה מפני
מה מת בחצי ימיו? Baali sheshanah harbeh vekara harbeh veshimesh chachamim harbeh
mipnei mah mes bachatzi yamav? Why did my husband die, he's so
young? ולא היה אדם מחזירה דבר, Velo hayah adam machzirah davar, nobody
was able to respond to her. פעם אחת נתארחתי אצלה, Paam achas
nisarachti etzlah, one time I visited her. Who's the I here? It's
אליהו הנביא, Eliyahu HaNavi, because this is from, okay, תנא דבי אליהו.
Tanna Debei Eliyahu.
It means, I
mean this is from אבות דרבי נתן, Avos DeRabbi Nassan, but it
basically means it's teachings about אליהו הנביא. Eliyahu HaNavi. One time I
visited her, והייתה משיחה כל אותו המאורע, Vehaysa mesichah kol oso hamaora,
she told me over this whole story. ואמרתי לה, Veamarti lah, I
said to her, בתי, Biti, my daughter, בימי נדותך מה הוא אצלך?
Bimei niddascha mah hu etzlech? How did you act together when you
were in נדה? Nidda? אמרה לי, Amra li, she said to me,
חס ושלום, Chas veshalom, אפילו באצבע קטנה לא נגע בי. Afilu beetzba
katanah lo naga bi. God forbid, he didn't even touch a pinky.
We were very careful to be separate. בימי ליבוניך מה הוא אצלך?
Bimei libunecha mah hu etzlech? How about in your white period? I'll
go back and discuss that in a minute. אכל עמי, Achal immi,
he ate with me, ושתה עמי, Veshassah immi, he drank with me,
וישן עמי, Veyashan immi, he slept with me בקירוב בשר, Bekiruv basar,
with a closeness of flesh.
We were wearing, we weren't wearing pajamas, we were together naked. But
don't worry, ולא עלתה דעתו על דבר אחר, Velo alsah daato al
davar acher, it never led to anything else. We were very careful,
we never had sex, but we were physically intimate during that time.
ואמרתי לה, Veamarti lah, I said to her, ברוך המקום שהרגו. Baruch
HaMakom sheharago.
Blessed is God that killed your husband. It's a good ניחום אבלים,
Nichum aveilim, right? שלא נשא פנים לתורה,
Shelo nasa
panim
laTorah, he did not, he was not able to misrepresent Torah. שהרי
אמרה תורה, Sheharei amrah Torah, ואל אשה בנדת טמאתה לא תקרב, Ve-el
isha beniddas tumasah lo sikrav,
you should not be having even physical intimacy, it's not only sex,
not like רבי פדת, Rabbi Pedas, even physical intimacy you should not
be having when you are a נדה, Nidda, and that explains why
he died. One minute, I have a lot to say about this.
כי אתא רב דימי אמר, Ki asa Rav Dimi amar, when Rav
Dimi came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, he said, מיטה חדה הואי.
Mita chada havai. It was a wide bed. So the reason they
weren't sleeping together, they were in the same bed, but they weren't
sleeping next to each other naked, the reason they thought it was
okay was because it was a wide bed and they were at
opposite ends of the bed. And even then that was wrong, because
they shouldn't be in the same bed even if they weren't next
to each other, and that's why he died. Which is interesting because
some people will often like, the husband and wife will go somewhere
and they'll be, you know, and if they're staying somewhere for שבת
Shabbos and they give them a bedroom and it only has one
bed, what do you do with that? Can you put a body
pillow in between and sleep at separate ends of the bed? The
general answer is no, and this גמרא Gemara makes it clear, you
know, that even a wide bed is a problem. So, and then
אמר רב יצחק בר יוסף סינר מפסיק בינו לבינה. Amar Rav Yitzchak
bar Yosef sinar mafsik beino leveinah. No,
here's why it was okay: she was wearing some type of an
apron, you know, from her waist down, and therefore so it was
sort of like הוא בבגדו והיא בבגדה. Hu bevigdo vehi bevigdah. They
might have been בקירוב בשר Bekiruv basar from the waist up, but
not on the waist down, and because they were wearing something they
assumed that it was okay. But again we see it wasn't okay.
You can't be husband and wife together in the same bed. Now
I need to say something briefly about this because I do want
to move on to the next משנה. Mishna. So first of all,
this גמרא Gemara, serves as a basis for a lot of ראשונים's
Rishonim understanding: what are the הרחקות Harchakos of husband and wife together?
First of all, as Michael has been mentioning a few times, we
have this issue of זב וזבה Zav veZava eating together. If that's
a concern that it would lead to sex, that leads some ראשונים
Rishonim to saying that therefore husband and wife when the wife is
a נדה Nidda should not be eating together, at least off of
the same table. And then it gets sort of, maybe it means
off of the same dish because in the time of the גמרא,
Gemara, a table was really like a private little, you know, little
serving table in front of you. So maybe they shouldn't be eating
off of the same dish together, or maybe there should be some
type of a היכר Hecker when the woman is a נדה Nidda
if there's nobody else in the house and so on. And they
learn that from the זב וזבה. Zav veZava. A lot of that
has to do with how you explain the זב וזבה Zav veZava
case. But anyway, that's one issue. But because of this תנא דבי
אליהו, Tanna Debei Eliyahu, they learn other things. Can't even touch a
pinky. It's interestingly, that issue about casual touch between husband and wife
when the wife is a נדה Nidda is not clear in the
גמרא, Gemara okay? The place where the ראשונים Rishonim learn it out
from is this story where she said חס ושלום Chas veshalom he
didn't even touch a pinky. Okay, talking about casual touch. Number two
is it speaks, it also says אכל עמי ושתה עמי, Achal immi
veshassah immi, which suggests to some ראשונים Rishonim you shouldn't be eating
and drinking together, husband and wife, or again, without some type of
a היכר. Hecker. The final thing is that the version of this
in אבות דרבי נתן Avos DeRabbi Nassan says, has אליהו Eliyahu asking
her, did you perhaps like hand to him the food? And she
said, you know, no, no, I didn't, you know, you know, let
me just quote it from תוספות Tosafos as it one minute. He
says like this, he
says שמא הבאת לו השמן שמא הבאת לו הפך? Shema hevesa lo
hashemen shema hevesa lo hapach? And then he says, and then it
says and maybe you handed him the food and in the process
he touched you? And then she touched him and she said חס
ושלום. chas veshalom. Oh no, I'm sorry, you brought him the food
and in the process he touched you, you were handing him the
food? חס ושלום, chas veshalom, he didn't even touch a pinky. So
that then leads to some ראשונים rishonim saying you shouldn't even be
handing things one to the other when the woman is a נדה,
niddah, it will lead to touching. Although most ראשונים rishonim realize that
that's not in the גמרא Gemara and that's a later מנהג. minhag.
So on the one hand this גמרא, Gemara although it's really only
in passing in this אליהו Eliyahu story, serves as the basis for
ראשונים rishonim to learn out a lot of other הרחקות harchakot between
husband and wife. Now I want to say something though about this
ימי ליבונה, yemei libunah, which is what is this white period? So
you'd say well, a woman after she stops bleeding she waits seven
clean days. But that's only our contemporary practice of נדה. niddah. In
the time of this story, whatever the time of the גמרא, that
was only, a seven clean days was only for a woman who
was a זבה. zavah, So she says okay, it means when you
were a זבה, what did you do during the clean period? It's
a little funny because we're talking about נדה niddah and זבה, it's
unusual. So תוספות Tosafot says no, there's a practice after the time
of נדה, niddah, תוספות Tosafot sort of reads in like the חומרא
דרבי זירא chumra de-Rabbi Zeira into this story and says that that
was a practice after the seven days of נדה דאורייתא niddah de-Oraita
going to the מקוה, mikvah, then you were done with your דאורייתא
de-Oraita of נדה, niddah, then you had seven clean days for your
rabbinic, and during those clean days, although it was only rabbinic, that's
why they were more lenient. And even though, and even so, that's
why he died young. Now of course A, that's very difficult because
number one it reads חומרא דרבי זירא chumra de-Rabbi Zeira back into
the story, which was much later, and number two you know when
it's the consequence, מת בחצי ימיו נשא פנים בתורה שלא כהלכה, met
bachetzi yamav nasa fanim ba-Torah shelo ke-halacha, all those things, for something
which was a sort of rabbinic issue seems quite heavy. I think
that the פשט peshat of this story is much more straightforward or
not much more straightforward, but anyway I have a much better read
of this story which is sort of following the theme of תוספות.
Tosafot. What is obvious if you read early חכמי אשכנז chachmei Ashkenaz
and even גאונים Geonim writings and so on is that there were
practices, common practices, not sort of halakhic practices, but practices by the
people to treat the period when the woman was actively bleeding more
strict than the period when the woman wasn't bleeding even though she
was still a נדה. niddah. And that centered around taboos associated with
the menstruation itself, even though it wasn't about her halakhic status of
a נדה. niddah. And we actually do find that they say after
the woman stops bleeding she would go and bathe herself in a
bath, not necessarily in a מקוה, clean herself off, wear white or
whatever, and then they start talking about less stringencies about the distance
between husband and wife. And it seems that that is, and that
we know was very ancient, you know, and it might have even
been in the time of the תורה, Torah, these taboos that were
not specifically around the הלכה. halakha. And that seems to be what
is going on here. And the way I read this is the
following: is that the גמרא is very clear that it treats נדה,
niddah, I mean it's almost absurd it brings in the question about
cheese and meat and so on. But nevertheless what it's saying is
נדה niddah is not special. It's just like any other עבירה, we're
concerned about, you can't have sex, we have to do certain safeguards.
No taboos, no superstition, no, you know, what do you call it,
kooties because of bleeding. It's just about an עבירה and safeguards. And
then this story is showing the contrast. Here this תלמיד, talmid, he
might have learned משנה Mishnah and מקרא, Mikra, but he didn't really
know הלכה. halakha. And he was following the common practices of the
taboos. So during the five days of bleeding, they were super strict.
He didn't even touch אצבע קטנה, etzba ketana, he didn't eat, very
very strict, stricter than the rabbis were because it was the taboos
of the bleeding. But then when she wasn't bleeding it was too
lenient. No restrictions, they slept together in the same bed. And that's
why he said נשא פנים בתורה שלא כהלכה, nasa fanim ba-Torah shelo
ke-halacha, that the whole problem is you think you're going to be
so פרום frum and have all these חומרות chumros when she's actively
bleeding, but it's going to lead to leniencies, it's a חומרא chumra
that leads to קולא. kula. And this is the wrong approach to
take with הלכות נדה. hilchos niddah. It's not about taboos and it's
not about all these crazy ways of being distant. It's just about
like normal הלכה halakha about safeguards and not transgressing and that's it.
And I think an amazing thing when you read through all of
מסכת נדה Masechet Niddah like we did a few months ago is
that this idea that there were taboos, which is very clear from
the extra-Gemara literature, is completely absent from נדה. niddah. The חז"ל Chazal
insist that this is just הלכה. halakha. It's just about an איסור
issur and הלכה halakha and none of this other type of stuff.
Now the problem is that those taboos do wind up resurfacing, and
that's an interesting question in the history of הלכות נדה. hilchos niddah.
But that's what I think is going on in this story, to
contrast a strictly halakhic approach that we have on the עמוד א'
amud aleph with a taboo-oriented approach that we find in this story.
And that's what, and that's what it was, you know, you think
you're being פרום frum and actually it leads to קולות, kulos,
yes.
Bobby. Anybody having a problem with this thought that she's told, this
is the reason why your husband died young? Let's look at this
realistically.
Yeah I know the גמרא right,
we all know that a lot of men were doing this and
they didn't die young.
Right. So anyway so yes Bobby the גמרא is not focusing on
this from a pastoral perspective. The best I could say is that
here was this woman that was creating a real challenge to not.
Not just she was asking a theological question and going in private
and talking to her rabbi about why did this happen. She was
going to the בתי מדרש Batei Midrash to make a public issue
about it and challenging what does it mean to be observant or
how and whatever. So I think that, you know, I think that's
a little bit explains why he felt he needed to give her
a strong answer. All right, but...
It's more than a strong
answer, I'm sorry.
The image of God that emerges
that kills, הרג, harag, the story
that God, you know...
But remember, this is not a רב, rav, this is אליהו. Eliyahu.
I understand, but no, it is still harsh. It is still harsh.
ברוך המקום, Baruch Hamakom, right, killed your husband? Right, right. אליהו Eliyahu
was retired because he was too harsh.
All right, fine. I have...
I hear it. The phrase God killed, blessed is God that killed,
that was a little... that was quite harsh. But I do think
that she needed a strong answer because she was seen as really
threatening, you know, the... the practices and the laws. Okay, so that's
why, that's what's behind it.
Yes.